<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian life and death of Mistris Katherin Brettergh, late wife of Master VVilliam Brettergh, of Bretterghoult in the countie of Lancaster, Gentleman, who departed this world the last of May with the manner of a bitter conflict she had with Satan and blessed conquest by Christ before her death, [to the great?] glorie of God, and comfort of all beholders.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02733</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12864</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24535184</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24535184</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27766</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02733)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27766)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1853:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian life and death of Mistris Katherin Brettergh, late wife of Master VVilliam Brettergh, of Bretterghoult in the countie of Lancaster, Gentleman, who departed this world the last of May with the manner of a bitter conflict she had with Satan and blessed conquest by Christ before her death, [to the great?] glorie of God, and comfort of all beholders.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, and are to be sold by Thomas Pauier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also published with title: A brief discourse of the Christian life and death of Mistris Katherin Brettargh--Cf. NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C³.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brettargh, Katharine, 1579-1601.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27766:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27766:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIAN LIFE AND DEATH, OF MISTRIS KATHERIN BRETTERGH, late wife of Maſter <hi>VVilliam Brettergh,</hi> of Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terghoult, in the Countie of Lancaſter Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; <hi>who departed this world the last of May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the manner of a bitter conflict ſhe had with <hi>Satan, and bleſſed conquest by Christ, before her death,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> glorie of God, and comfort of <hi>all beholders.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MICHA. 7.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Reioyce not against me, O mine enemie: though I fall, I ſhall riſe againe: And when I ſit in darkeneſſe, the Lord ſhall be a light vnto me.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM. 37.37.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the vpright man, and behold the iuſt: for the end of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ace.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Pauier.</hi> 1612.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27766:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27766:2"/>
            <head>The holy life and Chriſtian death, of <hi>Mistris Katherin Brettergh.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Gentlewoman was borne in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Iohn Bruen</hi> of <hi>Bruenſtaple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Eſquire, well deſcended, and of an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent houſe. Her education before her mariage was ſuch, as became the profeſſion of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, in godlines and puritie of life and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and wel beſéemed the <hi>houſe where ſhe was brought vp.</hi> The Scriptures ſhee knew from a child,<note place="margin">Stapleford.</note> and by reading thereof, gained ſuch knowledge, that ſhée was able rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilie to apply them when occaſion was offered, as we may ſee at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that ſo fitly, and effectually, that ſhée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> dailie meditation. For the things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>erate, and ſober, and by her Chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath, ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght teach many Gentlewomen, how vaine the pleaſures and faſhions of this world are, and how farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to bring that peace to a diſtreſſed heart, that the embracing of true Religion can.</p>
            <p>She vſed not to gad abroad with wandring <hi>Dinah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 34.1. 1. Sam. 1.9.12.</note> to dancing gréenes, markets, or publike aſſemblies: but rather with <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> did chuſe to tread vpon the duſt of the Sanctuarie, and walke in the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Sion: yea,</hi> with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 84.10.</note> 
               <hi>rather to bee a doore-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the houſe of God, then to haue ſocietie with the wicked, or to dwell in the tents and taberna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s of the vngodly.</hi> The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day was alwaies deere and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>come to her, what time ſhee would not be without the word preached, though many times ſhe went farre for it. <hi>Her delight was ſtill to conſecrate it glorious to the Lord.</hi> And as it is ſaid of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 22.19.</note> 
               <hi>his heart melted when he heard the law;</hi> ſo may it be ſaid of her, her heart was ſo tender and full of compaſſion, that oftentimes ſhee was ſeene to heare Sermons, reade, pray, and meditate with teares.</p>
            <p>She made conſcience of all ſinne; yea, of the leaſt ſin, ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:27766:3"/>worldlings count no ſinne: ſhe neuer vſed to ſwearedath great nor ſmall, nor yet to abuſe her tongue with vaine or vnſeemely ſpeeches; no not ſo much as a ieſt-lie or immodeſt word; neither durſt ſhe name the name of God, or take his titles in her mouth, without great reuerence. In priuate ſpeech where ſhee might ſpeake with profit, ſhée did it ſo well, that her ſpeeches might haue been deliuered by a ſtronger veſſell then her ſelfe: her words being ſo well ſeaſoned, and proceeding from ſuch a ſanctified heart, did alwaies <hi>miniſter grace to the hearers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To reade,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 16.3.</note> to pray, to ſing, to meditate, was her daily exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe; and her chiefeſt delight was in the holy ſociety of the Saints vpon earth (which I ſay not for any cauſe, but onely to ſhew the fountaine from whence her godlie end flowed, and that the world may ſée ſome there bée which chuſe rather to bée ioyned with the people of God,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note> then to <hi>enioy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon;</hi> and theſe I doubt not haue choſen the better part.) Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, the precepts of the Lord were pretious vnto her, for from her childhood ſhée feared God and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> knowledge and ſanctification did ioyne in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects whereof did appeare in her life, and was ſéene at he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the glorie of God, and comfort of all beholders.</p>
            <p>She was not like the ſimple Popiſh women of our daies, which <hi>are euer learning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>and neuer able to come to the knowledge of the truth;</hi> but rather like the noble men and women of <hi>Berea,</hi> which receiued the word of God with readineſſe,<note place="margin">Act. 17.11.12.</note> and were able to diſcerne of <hi>Pauls</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> preaching. But why doe I ſpeake of Popiſh women whoſe vnderſtandings are darker then the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of <hi>Egypt?</hi> Let vs come and examine many other which ſéeme to deteſt Poperie, and aske them a reaſon of their faith; they can tell you a tale of their ruffes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their pride, and their vanities but for Religion, it is the leaſt thing they regard, or ſéeke to know: which I ſpeake not ſo much to ſolace my ſelte in the ſins and ſimplicitie of others, as earneſtly deſiring al Gentlewomen, that either knew this holy Saint of God, or hereafter ſhall heare of her, in ſtead of your glaſſes at home, wherein you pricke and prune, and pin your ſelues, to looke into this glaſſe before your eyes, that ſo her life, and death, may bée an example for you to fol ow.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:27766:3"/>
            <p> When ſhée was about twentie yéeres old, (by the conſent of herſelfe, and her friends) ſhe was married to a young <hi>Lancaſhire Gentleman, Maſter William Brettergh of Bretterghoult</hi> néere <hi>Liuerpole:</hi> one that likewiſe embraced Religion ſincerelie, and for the ſame indured many grieuances at the hands of Papiſts.</p>
            <p>Two yéeres and more ſhe liued after ſhée was married, and had iſſue onelie one <hi>Daughter:</hi> during which time,<note place="margin">Anna Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh.</note> this couple liued together in ſuch mutuall ioy and comfort, as well beſéemed the children of God, which make profeſſion of his truth. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this Gentlewoman came from the habitations of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to dwell in <hi>Sodome,</hi> amidſt the tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 120.5.</note> that is to ſay, among inhumane bands of brutiſh Papiſts, induring many temporall grieuances from them; yet her knowledge, patience, mild inclination, and conſtancie for the truth was ſuch, as that her husband was further builded vp in Religion by her meanes, and his face daily more and more hardened againſt the diuell, and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> plaguie agents; the <hi>Popiſh Recuſants, Church-papiſts,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>all Proteſtants,</hi> which ſwarmed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> parts.</p>
            <p>It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnknowne to <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> what horſes and cattell of her husbands were killed vpon his grounds in the night, moſt barbarouſlie at two ſeuerall times by Seminarie Prieſts (no queſtion) and Recuſants that lurked thereabouts. And what a loſſe and hindrance it was vnto him, being all the ſtocke hée had on his grounds to any purpoſe. This fell out not long after ſhée was married to him; yet this was ſo farre from diſmaying her, or working ſuch paſſions in her, as are common to her ſex, that ſhe rather <hi>reioyced, then ſorrowed;</hi> turning it into matter of praiſing God, and ſubmitting her ſelfe to his good prouidence.<note place="margin">n="*" Iohn Wrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinton Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Richard Orme. Raph Heaton, &amp;c. and many moe.</note> Oft ſhe would haue ſaid, It is good that ſuch things be; but woe be to them that doe them. It is good in God, thereby to chaſten his children, and preuent ſome ſinne, which he ſaw vs like to fall into. It is good in reſpect of Gods Church, that the weake may be confirmed in the truth, and that Papiſtrie may bée diſgraced, when the world ſhall ſée ſuch wickedneſſe flow from it. It is good in God, that ſo the wicked may be without excuſe at the day of iudgement, when their conſcience ſhall tell them, that howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer God ſuffers them to doe ſuch villanie for ſome iuſt cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:27766:4"/>knowne to himſelfe; yet they commit it onely of malice and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge. Oftentimes alſo in theſe vexations, ſhe would haue ſaid; the mercies of God are infinite, who doth not onely by his word, but alſo by his iuſtice, make vs fit for his kingdome. Little doe our enemies know, what good by theſe things they doe vnto vs, and what wracke they bring to their owne kingdome, while they ſet foorth the wickedneſſe thereof. Many times ſhee would pray that God would forgiue them, which had done them this hurt, and ſend them repentance: and ſhe would call vpon her huſband, that he would doe the like,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.44.</note> and <hi>bleſſe them that curſed him.</hi> And for feare leſt her huſband ſhould faile in that point through in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie and weakeneſſe,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.5.</note> as it is ſaid of <hi>Iob, who offered ſacrifice for his ſonnes, leſt peraduenture they ſhould ſinne, and blaſpheme God in their hearts:</hi> ſo ſhe neuer failed, but daily prayed vnto the Lord to ſanctifie her huſbands thoughts, and direct his hearts, right, onelie to ſeeke Gods glorie, without either deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, or ſatiſfying his owne affections. So humble was her ſpirit, ſo carefull to auoid and preuent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and others; and ſo mild of nature, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſoftened the malicious heart of <hi>Eſau</hi> his brother:<note place="margin">Gen. 33.3.4. 1. Sam. 24. 17.18.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> by his kindneſſe in the caue, changed the fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of <hi>Saul,</hi> into wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and confeſſing that <hi>Dauid</hi> was more righteous then he: ſo ſhe by her meekeneſſe, humilitie, and vnſpotted carriage in the world, forced ſome of the aduerſaries to Religion, to ſpeake well of her.</p>
            <p>For her life, ſhe was well reported of all that knew her. Piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and bountifull was ſhee to the poore, and ſlacked no oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to doe good wherein ſhee could; but conſtantly held her courſe, and kept her times of praying, reading, and meditating, (wherein ſhe had plentifull gifts) and continuallie vſed the ſame at ſuch times as were fitting for her ſtate, ſex, and calling. At the exerciſes of Religion, as prayer and inſtruction in her fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, ſhe would not be wanting: beſides priuate prayer, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation which ſhe omitted not but vſed daily, both in her cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 24.63.</note> as alſo abroad ſecretlie and ſolitarilie in the orchard, garden, or fields, as <hi>Iſaacks</hi> manner was. In reading the Scriptures ſhée vſed euermore to taſke her ſelfe, eight chapters a day at the leaſt, and for the time which ſhe ſaw euill or idlie ſpent, without doing
<pb facs="tcp:27766:4"/>ſome good, ſhe vſed to call <hi>the time of tentation.</hi> Many times alſo ſhe would reade ſome godly writer, or expoſitor of Scripture, or in the booke of Martyrs; and was ſeene to weepe moſt bitterly, when either ſhe had read of that which touched her affections neere, or of the cruell martyrdome, which the deare children of God were put vnto, by the cruell and wicked tyrants of former daies.</p>
            <p>For Poperie, ſhe ſaw it ſo groſſe and fooliſh,<note place="margin">Exod. 23.13. Pſalm. 16.4 Epheſ. 5.3. Iudg. 6.31.32. Eccl. 4.25.28.</note> that ſhee would not once name it, except it were to argue againſt it, but neuer for it: ſo zealous was ſhe of Gods glorie, and loued the truth ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, that ſhe would not once open her mouth to plead for <hi>Baal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sin aboue all things was batefull vnto her, for there at ſhée would haue grieued, as well when ſhe had ſeene it in others, as in her ſelfe. One or two examples I cannot omit, wherein ſhée bewraied a worthie ſpirit, ſanctified by the ſpirit of God, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for all the aſſaults of Satan. On a time, as her huſband and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were riding toward the Church, he was angry with his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>husband</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>th ſhe) <hi>I feare your heart is not right to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that can be thus angrie for a trifle:</hi> And weeping ſhe ſaid further, <hi>you muſt pray againſt this your affection, and alwaies be ſure your anger be of God, for elſe how dare you appeare this day before his Miniſter? and offer vp your prayers in the publike congregation of the Saints of God?</hi> Another time, a tenant of her huſbands, being behind with his rent, ſhée deſired him to beare yet with him a quarter of a yeere, which hee did: and when the man brought his money, with teares ſhee ſaid to her husband: <hi>I feare you doe not well to take it of him, though it bee your right, for I doubt he is not well able to pay it, and then you oppreſſe the poore.</hi> So great a compaſſion had ſhe of other mens wants, that all things being duly conſidered, and rightly weighed, me thinks I may ſay of her, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Timothie, I know none like minded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus after ſhe was married,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.20.</note> ſhe continued in the things ſhee had learned, and held her profeſſion with ſuch ſinceritie, that the common enemies to our religion (the very Papiſts) had nothing to ſay againſt her, but confeſſed her life was vnreproueable. And as for the godly that knew her, they alwaies acknowledged that modeſtie, and vertuous carriage in her, ioyned with knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:27766:5"/>and practiſe of all the duties of religion, that they had iuſt cauſe to report of her, as of a ſound and faithfull profeſſor of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Two yéeres, and ſomewhat more ſhe liued with her husband, till about Whitſontide, it pleaſed God to ſend her that ſicknes whereof on Whitſonday ſhe died.</p>
            <p>Her ſickneſſe tooke her in the manner of <hi>a hot burning Ague,</hi> which made her according to the nature of ſuch diſeaſes, now and then to talke ſomewhat idl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and through the tempters ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie, which abuſed the infirmitie of her body to that end, as hée oftentimes vſeth to doe in many, from idle words, to deſcend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a heauie conflict, with the infirmitie of her owne ſpirit; from the which, yet the Lord preſently and wonderfully deliuered her, giuing ſo ioyfull an iſſue to the tentation, that ſhe might well vſe the words of the Prophet, as afterwards ſhe did: <hi>For a moment, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 54.8. May 23.</note> 
               <hi>thou diddeſt hide thy face from me, for a little ſeaſon, but with euerlaſting mercie thou haddeſt compaſſion on me.</hi> On <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday</hi> ſeuen-night before <hi>Whitſunday,</hi> what time ſhe ſickned, ſhe began to feele ſome little infirmitie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> then ſhe had wont to ſhew, but ſhe ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>uer came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> night it increaſed vpon her,<note place="margin">May 25.</note> and the aſſault of the enemie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be ſharpe, and ſo continued till the next day at afternoone; what time God deliuered her, and ſent her peace and comfort of conſcience, and ſo increaſed the ſame in her continually til ſhe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed The manner of her affliction was this.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">M. William Brettergh. M. William Fox M. Edward Aſpinwall. M. Iohn Brettergh Miſtris Maud Brettergh. Miſtris Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtica Fox. William Woodward. Elizabeth Challoner.</note> the ſeueritie of Gods iuſtice, and the greatnes of her ſins began to come into her mind, which much afflicted her, and ſhée would often ſpeake of it. Then ſhe accuſed her ſelfe of pride, that ſhée had delighted too much in her ſelfe, and her beautie. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſhe thought ſhee had no faith, but was full of hypocriſie, and had not imbraced Religion ſo earneſtlie, nor glorified God ſo worthilie (eſpecially with her tongue, which oft ſhée repeated) nor loued him ſo ſincerely as ſhée ought to haue done. Sometime ſhe would caſt her Bible from her, and ſay: <hi>It was indeed the booke of life, but ſhe had read the ſame vnprofitablie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore feared it was become to her the booke of death.</hi> Sometimes ſhe would ſay her ſinnes had made her a pray to Satan, a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle to the world, a diſgrace to religion, and a ſhame to her husband, kinred, and all true Chriſtians: and here ſhee would
<pb facs="tcp:27766:5"/>weepe bitterly. Sometime the originall corruption wherein ſhe was borne, troubled her, and the ſinnes of her parents, and the common parents of all, <hi>the eaters of the forbidden fruit:</hi> as if that had made her vnworthie of God, and were then laid to her charge. Many times ſhee accuſed her ſelfe of impatience, be wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the want of feeling Gods ſpirit, and making doubt of her e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and ſuch like infirmities. She wiſhed that ſhe had neuer béen borne, or that ſhe had been made any other creature, rather then a woman. She cried out oftentimes, <hi>Woe, woe, woe, &amp;c. a weake, a wofull, a wretched, a forſaken woman,</hi> and ſuch like pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull complaints againſt her ſelfe, with teares continually trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from her eies. Shée complained of grieuous thirſt, ſuch as all the water in the ſea could not quench (and yet when drinke was giuen her, ſometimes refuſed it, ſometimes tooke a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of it) ſweate burſt out vpon her excéedingly, and ſometimes her body borned extreamely. <hi>So it ſeemed the ſorrowes of death hemmed her in, and the griefes of hell laid hold vpon her.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> prayer, and once when ſhe ſhould haue ſaid, <hi>Deade vs not into tentation,</hi> ſhe made a ſtop, ſaying, <hi>I may not pray; I may not pray (being interrupted, as ſhe ſaid, by Satan)</hi> and ſo ſhewed much diſcomfort: howbeit ſhe was not left till ſhe could both pray, ane make confeſſion of her faith with ſpeciall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to her ſelfe. Beſides theſe fierie darts of Satan, ſhee was once or twice troubled with vaine ſpeeches, as of her child, the killing of her husbands cattell, that ſhe thought ſhe ſaw a fire by her, &amp;c. But euery one ſaw that theſe things proceeded of weakeneſſe, emptineſſe of her head, and want of ſleepe, which her diſeaſe would not affoord her.</p>
            <p>Theſe fits though they were for the time grieuous to her ſelfe, and diſcomfortable to her friends: yet were they neither long nor continual, but in the very middeſt of them, would ſhe oftentimes giue teſtimonie of her faith, ſtriuing and fighting againſt her tentations. Many times when the ſtanders by iudged her afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at the ſharpeſt, would ſhe call vpon God, lifting vp her eies and hands to heauen, <hi>and deſire him to giue her ſtrength againſt her tentations.</hi> Many times with a chearefull countenance ſhe would defire thoſe that were by not to faint, nor giue her ouer, but conſtantly to pray, and helpe her againſt the tempter. Once
<pb facs="tcp:27766:6"/>in the middeſt of her tentation, being demanded by <hi>Maſter Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Foxe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">William Fox.</note> 
               <hi>whether ſhe did beleeue the promiſes of God or no? and whether ſhe could pray?</hi> ſhe anſwered: <hi>O that I could, I would willingly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marke 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>but he will not let me. Lord I beleeue, helpe my vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe:</hi> which ſhe pronounced with a ſtill low voice. And when he replied, that if ſhe had a deſire to pray and beleeue, ſhée did pray and beleeue, and that ſo effectuallie, that hell gates ſhould not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome her, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>God accepteth it according to that a man hath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>not according to that a man hath not:</hi> ſhe was much comforted thereby.</p>
            <p>Once after a great conflict with Satan, ſhe ſaid: <hi>Satan reaſo not with me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh.</note> 
               <hi>I am but a weake woman, if thou haue any thing to ſay, ſay it to my Chriſt; he is my aduocate, my ſtrength, and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and he ſhall pleade for me.</hi> Sometimes when ſhe was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with the accuſation of her ſins, and want of féeling Gods mercy, ſhee would with many a pitifull ſob and much wéeping, <hi>pray to the Lord Ieſus Chriſt to help and comfort her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh.</note> 
               <hi>a poore wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, diſtreſſed woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Edward Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinwall.</note> and requeſt others to pray for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. And when ſhe was moued to make confeſſion of her faith, ſhe would do it oftentimes, ſaying the Apoſtles <hi>Creed,</hi> and concluding the ſame with words of application to her ſelfe: I beléeue the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>[my]</hi> ſins, the reſurrection of <hi>[my]</hi> body, and eternall life <hi>[to me] Amen.</hi> And hauing done, ſhe would pray God to confirme her in that faith, euer concluding with the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly and reuerontly as any that were preſent. A Chriſtian friend, who by his daily attendance on her, diſcharged the duty of a faithfull Chriſtian,<note place="margin">William Woodward.</note> ſtanding by told her, <hi>that no tentation had befallen her, but that which appertained to the child of God, and that God is faithfull and true, and had promiſed to giue an iſſue with the tentation:</hi> whereat ſhe expreſſed great comfort.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Edward Aſpinwal,</hi> a faithful profeſſor of the truth, and <hi>a true Iſraelite,</hi> was much with her in the time of her ſicknes, and miniſtred much heauenly inſtruction vnto her, and comforted her at all times with apt places of Scripture, méeting with her ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: and ſo put the ſword of the ſpirit into her hand. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to her the moſt plentifull comforts of God vnto his Church, in the <hi>40.41.42.</hi> and <hi>43.</hi> Chapters of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> vttered in ſuch ſpéeches and phraſes,<note place="margin">Eſa. 40.1.2.28.29.30.31.</note> as might moſt fitlie anſwere her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforts.
<pb facs="tcp:27766:6"/>Alſo he directed her to conſider the Paſſion and Práyer of our Sauiour Chriſt, for all his,<note place="margin">Eſa. 41.8.9.10.13.14.17.18. Iſa. 42.1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.13.14. 15.16. Eſa. 43.1.2.5.25. Matth. 11.28.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn 17. Matth. 26. Luk. 22.23.</hi> But ſpecially did he often inculcate that ſwéete inuitation of our Sauiour: <hi>Come vnto me all you that trauell and be heauie laden, I will eaſe you.</hi> But the difficultie ſhe had ſometimes to apply theſe generals vnto her own ſoule in particular, made the caſe more ful of anguiſh to her ſelf, and feareful and lamentable to the ſtanders by: Albeit ſhe acknowledged Gods <hi>Maieſty, mercy, faithfulneſſe, and truth;</hi> yet ſtill complained ſhe of her owne weaknes, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines, and could hardly appropriate each thing to her ſelfe.</p>
            <p>To help her ſome what herein (for properly otherwiſe, it is the peculiar work of the <hi>holy ſpirit of God,</hi> to perſwade the hart and ſoule of her particular intereſt in theſe general promiſes) ſhe was told that the <hi>Almighty</hi> who was <hi>mercifull,</hi> as ſhe had proued, and <hi>faithfull</hi> as ſhe confeſſed; intended all theſe mercies to as many as he did call and make promiſe to. And that hee called her ſhe muſt néeds confeſſe, both becauſe that then ſhe not only her ſelfe read, but heard others reade thoſe bleſſed words of God vnto her: and alſo for that in former times, ſhe had bin touched with the loue of God, and that his truth: and had well profited in the deteſtation of ſinne, and imitation of her Sauiour in a holy life. And for the proofe thereof; ſhe was wiſhed to remember in former times her <hi>Baptiſine,</hi> her frequenting of <hi>Sermons,</hi> &amp; often receiuing the moſt comfortable repaſt of the holy <hi>Communion,</hi> her daily, and almoſt continual exerciſe of <hi>reading, meditating, and praying, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo he aſſured her, that neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent agony ſhe was in, nor the ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches then in that diſtreſſe, tending to the ſignification of deſpaire, extorted from her, were any iuſt cauſes, why either ſhe, or any that heard her, ſhould iudge fearefullie of her, becauſe all might ſee the fault was not in her <hi>will,</hi> as appeares by her prayers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, plaints, ſighs, teares, and grones to God for mercy, and full aſſurance in the blood of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but in her <hi>iudgement,</hi> not able at that time to diſcerne the waies of the Almightie: And therein (he told her) ſhe was made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formable, not only to many the holy Saints of God, <hi>Iob, Ieremy, Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 3.1. &amp;c. Ier. 20.14. Iob 6.4.8.9. Iob 16.9. Lament. 3. &amp;c.</note> &amp; others more, but alſo to her head, our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> of whom we reade, <hi>that ſome haue curſed the day of their birth, and called for their end, and darkenes to couer them: They haue been as men without
<pb facs="tcp:27766:7"/>hope, and ſwallowed vp in deſpaire: They haue cried how the wrath of God hath torne them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>and the terrors of the Almighty haue fought againſt them: They haue had no peace in their ſoules, nor comfort in their conſciences, their prayers haue bin ſhut from God, their ſinnes haue been terrible vnto them, crying that their iniquities had gone ouer their heads,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 38.4. &amp;c. Pſalm 71.7. Pſalm. 77.1.7. &amp;c. Pſalm. 51.5. Pſalm. 102.3. &amp;c. Rom. 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>and were a burthen too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie for them to beare: And they haue thought themſelues ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of ſhame and reproch, and as monſters vnto men: They were grieued for the ſinnes of their parents, and complained that they were deſolate, forſaken, and moſt miſerable and wretched in the world;</hi> yet for all this were they ſtill the deare children of God, as you are this day. (Nay (ſaith hée) I pray you conſider, what torments God inflicted vpon his deare Son vpon the Croſſe: did he not crie out,<note place="margin">Matth. 27<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>46. Matth. 26.38. Heb. 5.7. May 26.</note> 
               <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> He complained, that his <hi>ſoule was heauie vnto death;</hi> yet was hee <hi>heard in that which he feared,</hi> and God deliuered him. After this, he read vnto her the <hi>22.</hi> Pſalme, wherein <hi>Dauid</hi> complained, partly of his owne, but principally of the moſt bitter anguiſh which our Sauiour Chriſt endured, and ſuffered in body and ſoule, putting her in mind, that her caſe was not ſo bad as <hi>Dauids,</hi> nor much vnlike our Sauiours, who endured all that, and more for her; and therefore ſhe had no cauſe to feare, ſéeing <hi>Chriſt</hi> had obtained victorie, and would vndoubtedly bee with her, deliuer her, and eternally glorifie her with himſelfe for euermore; and ſo continually hee propounded to her ſuch comfortable places of Scripture, as might meet with her infirmities. This greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed her, and gaue her occaſion many times to call vpon God, for encreaſe of grace, and deliuerance from her grieuous tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: the which God of his accuſtomed goodnes vouchſafed, on <hi>Tueſday,</hi> about thrée a clocke in the afternoone, what time ſhée felt her ſelfe in very good meaſure deliuered from all her former feares and afflictions. But on <hi>Saturday</hi> next after, which was the day before her death, ſhe was wholly releaſed, and filled with ſuch inward comfort, that it greatly affected vs that ſaw it.</p>
            <p>This is the ſumme of that tentation which ſhee had, wherein what can any man ſée that might giue iuſt occaſion to report our religion comfortles, or the Gentle woman died deſpairing? This we are ſure of, that <hi>to be without tentation is the greateſt tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:27766:7"/>as alſo, that nothing befell her, which hath not befallen the holieſt of the children of God. And ſhe that conſidered her owne corruption (which how great it is in the beſt of Gods Saints, I need not ſay) and be thought her ſelfe of the puniſhment due ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, if God in iuſtice ſhould reward her, no maruel if ſhe brake out ſometime into heauy complaints. I make no queſtion it was the worke of God in her, to ſuffer Satan to accuſe her, and afflict her for her ſinnes, that ſo ſhée might the better ſee them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the hainouſnes of them, and before her departure repent her of them, and betake her wholly to <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the ſauing of her ſoule. And if it pleaſed God thus to make her poſſeſſe her ſins be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe died, let thoſe which neuer yet knew the waight of their ſinnes, be wiſe in time, and remember, that he ſhall neuer haue his ſinne forgiuen, which firſt or laſt doth not vndergoe a holy deſpaire for it, and acknowledge nothing to remaine in himſelfe, but matter of iudgement and condemnation: and comfort and eternall life to flow alone from <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for thoſe which haue learned to ſcoffe at the terrors of Gods children, and to cenſure ſuch, as are at ſometimes caſt downe with feeling the anger of God againſt ſinne, let them conſider the bleſſed iſſue that God gaue to the troubles of this Gentle woman, and let them acknowledge his worke in her. And if they will not doe this, but proceed to traduce the dead,<note place="margin">Fox. Acts and Mon. pag. 1904.61. pag. 1908.</note> then let them call to mind, thoſe of the Popiſh crue, and perſons of greater note among them, then this Gentlewoman was, which haue died moſt fearefully indeed. Cardinall <hi>Sadelot, Iacobus La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomus</hi> the Diuinitie Reader at <hi>Louaine, Hofmeſter</hi> the Frier, <hi>Guarlacus, Bomelius, Creſcentius</hi> the Cardinall, <hi>Stephen Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and diuers the bloodie perſecutors in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time, and ſome of the Popes themſelues, as namely,<note place="margin">n="*" Francis the Monke, one of the ten popiſh perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted in France, Anno Dom. 1601. See Haſen Mill. hiſtoria Ieſuirica, who ſets downe certaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the Ieſuites to this purpoſe.</note> 
               <hi>Pope Sixtus Quintus</hi> of late yeeres: all which died moſt fearefullie and miſerablie, and ſhewed manifeſt ſignes at their death, that their popiſh ſuperſtition was the condenmation of their ſoules. And if they will iudge of my religion by my death, let them acknowledge their religion is the doctrine of deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that the truth and faith which was able to fill the heart and tongue of this bleſſed Gentle woman at her death, with ſuch heauenly comforts, is the doctrine of Chriſt, reuealed from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:27766:8"/>that wee might liue and die in it.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Tueſday,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pl</note> till Whitian-eeuen, her comfort ſtill incerea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and tentations vaniſhed away. She would then very cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ioyne with the company in prayer, and ſinging Pſalmes, as occaſion offered,<note place="margin">Iohn Bruen Eſquire. William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. William Fox. Iohn Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. William Woodward. Iohn Holland. Maud Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. Scholaſtica Fox. 1. Pet. 4.17.18. Iohn Holland. William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. William Woodward.</note> and performed all ſuch duties as were méet for her in that eſtate. One day, her brother M. <hi>Iohn Bruen</hi> of <hi>Bruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapleford</hi> came from his houſe in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> to viſit her, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome kind ſalutation paſſed betwéene them, he ſaid vnto her: <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, be not diſmaied at your troubles, but remember what the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, that iudgement muſt begin at the houſe of God.</hi> To whom ſhe anſwered, as one that was alſo very ready in the Scriptures, with the very next words following: <hi>True it is, and if it begin at vs, and the righteous ſhall ſcarce be ſaued, where ſhal the ſinners and vngodly appeare?</hi> After that ſhe prayed with him, and ſung a Pſalme with him, as one that receiued great comfort by him, and acknowledged in him, a hart ſet to ſéek the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the kingdam of Chriſt. During this time, in the night with ſuch as waked with her, ſhe would pray and rehearſe for her comfort many texts of Scripture, and namely the 8. to the Romanes, many times concluding and cloſing vp that ſhée read, or repeated, with prayer, and moſt comfortable vſes and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations thereof to her ſelfe, with ſhew of ſuch ioy and comfort, that the hearers reioyced at it. When<note place="margin">n="*" Richar Orme, Iohn Holland, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh, William Woodward. William Fox. Reuel. 21.6. William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. William Fox. Pſal. 119.71.72. William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh.</note> ſhée receiued any meat, ſhee prayed God not onely to ſanctifie thoſe creatures for her bodilie ſuſtenance, but alſo to fill her ſoule with the waters of life, often repeating that of the Reuelation: <hi>To him that thirſteth, will I giue of the waters of life freelie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One time ſhe tooke her Bible in her hand, and ioyfully kiſſing it, and looking vp toward heauen, ſhe ſaid that of the Pſalme: <hi>O Lord, it is good for me that I haue bin afflicted, that I may learne thy ſtatutes: The law of thy mouth is better to me then thouſands of gold and ſiluer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another time ſhe called her husband to her and ſaid: <hi>O hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, beware of Papiſtrie, keepe your ſelfe holy before the Lord: Yeeld not to the abominations of the wicked, leſt they reioyce, and ſo you diſhonour God, and deſtroy your owne ſoule.</hi> Againe ſhe ſaid, <hi>Let my little child be brought vp among the children of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maud Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh.</note> 
               <hi>and in the true feare and knowledge of his Maieſtie; ſo ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:27766:8"/>I meet her in heauen, whom now I muſt leaue behind me on earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again,<note place="margin">William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. Rom. 8.15. William Fox.</note> ſometime ſhée would pray with a low voice to her ſelfe, and that ſaying of <hi>Paul, We haue not receiued the ſpirit of bondage to feare any more, but the ſpirit of adoption, whereby we crie, Abba father,</hi> was much in her mouth: and the laſt words <hi>Abba father,</hi> ſhe would double oftentimes ouer. She would ſing to her ſelfe the laſt verſe of the <hi>13.</hi> Pſalme.</p>
            <q>
               <l>I will giue thankes vnto the Lord, and praiſes to him ſing:</l>
               <l>Becauſe he hath heard my requeſt, and granted my wiſhing.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Finally, in theſe and ſuch like exerciſes and meditations, did ſhée ſpend the whole time of her ſickenes, after the Lord had once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged her heart, from the tentations of Satan.</p>
            <p>But vpon <hi>Saturday</hi> about eleuen of the clocke in the morning,<note place="margin">May 30.</note> the Lord diſcloſed himſelfe in mercy to her more plentifully then euer before; and as I may ſay, he dealt famlliarly with his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid: for from that time to her very death, which enſued the next day, the féeling of Satans tentations ſéemed quite to be baniſhed from her; ſo that ſhe made no ſhew of them, her thoughts were not occupied with the world, husband, child, or any thing elſe to our thinking; neither was her ſickenes trouble ſome to her, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it had been: but as one raiſed from death to life, or rauiſhed in ſpirit, ſo ſéemed ſhée to vs that ſtood by: her countenance ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, her tongue flowing with the praiſes of God, and her voice as moſt heauenly muſicke, and melodie of peace, ſounding praiſe, and honour, and glorie to God in a wonderfull manuer, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>About eleuen of the clocke ſhée began to tremble and quake a little,<note place="margin">William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. Maud Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. Elizabeth Challoner.</note> and withall ſhée aſked her husband it hée would helpe her with prayer to God againſt the tempter, ſaying, Will ye neither pray with mée, nor bring ſome godlie man that may put holy things into my mind, whereby I may bée able to reſiſt Satan? Hauing thus ſaid, ſhee vttered theſe words: <hi>O Lord God of my ſaluation, helpe my weakneſſe, pleade thou my cauſe, O God of truth, for in thee do I truſt.</hi> After this, they prayed together, and ſhe anſwered <hi>Amen</hi> to euery petition. Then after this ſhe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to reade ſome part of the Scripture: whereupon hee read vnto her the <hi>8.</hi> to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> the <hi>91. Pſalme,</hi> and the <hi>17.</hi> of <hi>Iohn,</hi> the which as he read, and came to the <hi>4.</hi> verſe, <hi>I haue fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb facs="tcp:27766:9"/>the worke which thou gaueſt me to do, and now glorifie me:</hi> ſhe deſired him to pauſe a while, &amp; then ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be thy name, O bleſſed Sauiour, perfect the worke, I humblie beſeech thee, which thou haſt begun in me.</hi> Then as he read the <hi>9.</hi> verſe, <hi>I pray not for the world, but for them which thou haſt giuen me, for they are thine:</hi> ſhe interrupted him againe ſaying, <hi>O Lord Ieſu, doeſt thou pray for me? O bleſſed and ſweet Sauiour, how wonderfull! how wonderfull! how wonderfull are thy mercies! Read on, ſaid ſhe, the bleſſedſt reading that euer I heard, the comfort whereof doth ſweeten my ſoule.</hi> Then reading verſe the <hi>22. And the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie which thou gaueſt mee, I haue giuen them, that they may bee one as we are one:</hi> with maruellous ioy ſhe vttered the words of <hi>Dauid</hi> many times ouer,<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>I confeſſe before the Lord his louing kindnes, and his wonderful works before the ſonnes of men: for he hath ſatisfied my ſoule, and filled my hungry ſoule with goodnes.</hi> When he came to the <hi>24.</hi> verſe, <hi>Father, I will that they which thou haſt giuen me, be with me, euen where I am, that they may behold my glorie, which thou haſt giuen me;</hi> Stay, ſaid ſhe, and let me meditate on the goodnes of the Lord, for this is the ſwée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſaying that euer came to my ſoule: for now I perceiue and feele the countenance of Chriſt my redeemer is turned towards me, and the bright ſhining beames of his mercie is ſpread ouer me: <hi>Oh happie am I that euer I was borne, to ſee this bleſſed day!</hi> Praiſe, praiſe, O praiſe the Lord for his mercies; for hee hath brought me out of darkenes,<note place="margin">Eſa. 27.1. Pſalm. 103.1.2.3.4.</note> and the ſhadow of death: hee hath deliuered my ſoule from the ſnare of the hunter, and hath taken me out of the den of Lions, euen from the iawes of <hi>Leuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, that piercing and crooked ſerpent,</hi> and hath ſet me in a place of reſt, and ſweete refreſhing: <hi>Oh praiſe the Lord O my ſoule, all that is within me praiſe his holy name: my ſoule praiſe thou the Lord, and forget not all his benefits, which forgiueth all thine iniquities, and healeth all thine infirmities: which hath redeemed thy life from the graue, and crowneth thee with mercie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.</hi> This ſhe often repeated: And then againe remembring the <hi>21.</hi> and <hi>22.</hi> verſes of the <hi>17.</hi> of <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſhee ſaid: <hi>O my ſweete Sauiour, ſhall I be one with thee, as thou art one with thy Father? And wilt thou glorifie mee with that glorie which thou haddeſt with the father before the world was? And doſt thou ſo loue mee
<pb facs="tcp:27766:9"/>(which am but duſt and aſhes) to make me partaker of glorie with Chriſt? What am I poore wretch, that thou art ſo mindfull of me?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 144.3. Pſal. 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>Oh how wonderfull! how wonderfull! how wonderfull is thy loue! Oh thy loue is vnſpeakeable, that haſt dealt ſo gratiouſlie with me! Oh I feele thy mercies, and oh that my tongue and heart were able to ſound forth thy praiſes as I ought, and as I willingly would doe! Oh that you all would helpe me to praiſe the holie one of Iſrael, the God of all conſolations!</hi> And thus for the ſpace of fiue houres together at the leaſt, ſhée continued praiſing and lauding the Lord, with ſuch a gladſome and heauenly counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, teſtifying ſuch inward ioy, from a comfortable feeling of the mercies of God in her ſoule, and vſing ſuch ſwéete ſentences, and ſugred phraſes of perfect and holy eloquence, as the truth thereof, if it could haue been taken, were admirable, continuing ſo many houres together; ſome part whereof was this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh my Lord, oh my God, bleſſed bee thy name for euermore, which haſt ſhewed me the path of life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 54.8.</note> 
               <hi>Thou didſt O Lord hide thy face from me for a little ſeaſon, but with euerlaſting mercie, thou haſt had compaſſion on me: And now bleſſed Lord thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable preſence is come, yea Lord, thou haſt had reſpect vnto thy handmaid, and art come with fulnes of ioy, and abundance of conſolations: O bleſſed be thy name O Lord my God.</hi> Then ſhée repeated part of the <hi>16.</hi> Pſalme, ſaying: <hi>The Lord is the portion of mine inheritance, wherefore my heart is glad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.59.11.</note> 
               <hi>and my tongue reioyceth: Thou wilt ſhew me the path of life: In thy preſence is fulnes of ioy; and at thy right hand there are pleaſures for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: Oh that I could therefore praiſe the Lord, as hee is worthie to be praiſed? I will ſing to the Lord, I will ſing to the praiſe of the God of Iſrael: come, come,</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>and helpe me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudges 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>O helpe me to praiſe the Lord.</hi> And with that ſhe began to ſing the third Pſalme, and continued to the end of the Pſalme, as perfectly, and with as ſweete a voice, as euer ſhe had before in her health; and concluded with the <hi>49.</hi> verſe of the <hi>106.</hi> Pſalme:</p>
            <q>
               <l>The Lord the God of Iſrael, be bleſt for euermore:</l>
               <l>Let all the people ſay Amen, praiſe ye the Lord therefore.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And after this ſhe ſaid, <hi>O praiſe the Lord, for hee hath filled me with ioy and gladnes of heart, and brought me from the gates of hell, and of death:</hi> repeating that of the <hi>16.</hi> Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.6.</note> 
               <hi>My line is
<pb facs="tcp:27766:10"/>fallen vnto me in a pleaſant place: yea I haue a faire heritage, for the Lord is the portion of mine inheritance: The place where I now am, is ſweete and pleaſant: Oh how pleaſant is the ſweete perfume of the place where I lie!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 30.23.</note> 
               <hi>It is ſweeter then Aarons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed perfume of principall ſpices: how comfortable is the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes I feele!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>It is like that odour that proceeds from the golden cenſor, that delights my ſoule. The taſte is precious: doe you not feele it? Oh ſo ſweete it is! yea ſweeter then myrrhe, the hony, or the hony combe. Let me therefore ſing againe, and againe vnto my Lord, and my God.</hi> Then ſhe did ſing the nineteenth Pſalme, beginning at the ſeuenth verſe, <hi>How perfect is the law of God, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo on to the end of the ſame. And after that ſpirituall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing, in ſinging of Pſalmes, ſhe then prayed vnto God faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and praiſed the Lord againe ioyfully. And being ſtill full of theſe, and ſuch like heauenly conſolacions, ſhe did ſing againe moſt hearthly, vnto the praiſe of God the <hi>136.</hi> Pſalme. <hi>Praiſe yee the Lord, for hee is good, for his mercie endureth for euer: &amp;c.</hi> In which Pſalme, <hi>for his mercie endureth for euer,</hi> is <hi>26.</hi> times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated. A Chriſtian friend comming in at the ſame time,<note place="margin">Maſter Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Fox.</note> which was about ſixe of the clocke in the euening, maruelling to ſee her exceeding ioyes, and heauenly harmonie, wherein ſhe continued with ſuch words and phraſes, that were ſo ſpirituall, prayed for the continuance of the ſame vnto the end:<note place="margin">William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gh. William Fox. William Woodward.</note> whereupon ſhee then hurſt out, relating further of her ioyes, ſaying: <hi>Oh the ioyes! the ioyes! the ioyes! that I feele in my ſoule! oh they be wonderfull! they bee wonderfull! they bee wonderfull!</hi> And after that, ſhee prayed for increaſe of faith, and that God would ſtrengthen her againſt tentations, with continuall crauing of cemiſſion of ſins, euer meditating of heauenly matters, as by her ſudden and often breaking out into heauenly ſpeeches, and praiſes, did appeare: for the ſame euening ſhe lying ſtill and ſilent for a while,<note place="margin">William Fox.</note> 
               <hi>one</hi> prayed her to remember the Lord Ieſus, and that ſhee would in her heart pray for conſtancie in her ioyfull courſe; whereupon ſhee anſwered with a delightſome and cheerefull countenance and comfortable voyce:<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.1.3.</note> 
               <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>ſo I doe, for the Lord is my light, and my ſaluation, whom then ſhall I feare? Though an hoſt pitch againſt me, yet my heart ſhall not bee afraid, for the Lord hath ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.31.</note> 
               <hi>I will not leaue thee, nor forſake thee. Indeed, I ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:27766:10"/>vtterly haue fainted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.13. Pſal. 108.1.</note> 
               <hi>but that I beleeued to ſee the goodneſſe of the Lord in the land of the liuing. And now my heart is readie, my heart is readie and prepared, yea, it panteth after thee O God: as the Hart brayeth after the riuers of water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſo panteth my ſoule af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee O God: my ſoule thirſteth for God, euen for the liuing God. When Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh.</note> 
               <hi>when ſhall I come and appeare before thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? &amp;c.</hi> Saying then further: <hi>Lord, ſith it hath pleaſed thee to prepare my heart, whether to life or death, thy will bee done, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of me to thine owne glorie: I am thine Lord, work thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed pleaſure and good will vpon me.</hi> And after this ſhe fell into a ſhort ſlumber, and awaking ſaid, as the ſpouſe ſaid vnto Chriſt in the Canticles: <hi>Oh come kiſſe me with the kiſſe of thy mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>for thy loue is better then wine. Oh how ſweete the kiſſes of my Sauiour bee?</hi> Then one ſaid vnto her,<note place="margin">William Fox.</note> alluding to that place of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> Reuel. <hi>3.8.</hi> and praying that the Lord would anoint her with the eye-ſalue of his grace, that ſhee might ſee and behold his glorie. To whom ſhe anſwered, <hi>Mine eyes are opened, mine eyes are opened, though for a while they were cloſed vp and ſhut; yet now I thanke my God, mine eyes are opened, and I doe feele and ſee the euerliuing mercies of my Chriſt:</hi> ſaying then further, as it is in the <hi>27.</hi> Pſalme: <hi>Thou ſaidſt, ſeeke my face: my heart anſwered to thee, O Lord I will ſeek thy face.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>O hide not therfore thy face from me, nor caſt thy ſeruant away in diſpleaſure, thou haſt been my ſuccour, leaue me not, nor forſake me, O God of my ſaluation.</hi> And being willed to commit her ſoule into the hands of Chriſt, ſhe ſaid: <hi>O Lord Ieſus, thou haſt redeemed me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. Pſal. 31.5. William Woodward. Matth. 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>pleade thou my cauſe, for into thy hands alone doe I commit my ſpirit, O thou God of truth.</hi> And then feeling more ioy to abound, <hi>one</hi> praiſing God with her for his mercies ſhewed toward her, ſhee further ſaid: <hi>I giue thee thanks O father, Lord of heauen &amp; earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe, and men of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and haſt opened them vnto me thy poore handmaid, which am but duſt and aſhes. O how merciful and maruellous gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious art thou vnto me! yea Lord, I feele thy mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">William Fox.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; I am aſſured of thy loue, &amp; ſo certaine am I therof, as thou art the God of truth, euen ſo ſure do I know my ſelfe to be thine, O Lord my God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.10.</note> 
               <hi>and this my ſoule knoweth right wel, and this my ſoule knoweth right wel:</hi> which ſpéech of her aſſurance, ſhe ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repeated. Preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:27766:11"/>this,<note place="margin">William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. Iob 19.25.26.27.</note> ſitting vp in her chaire, ſhe ſung the fourth Pſalme; and then being laid downe againe in her bed, ſhee confidently ſpake theſe words: <hi>I am ſure that my redeemer liueth, and that I ſhall ſee him at the laſt day, whom I ſhall ſee, and mine eye ſhal behold: and though after my skin, wormes deſtroy this bodie, yet ſhall I ſee God in my fleſh with theſe eyes, and none other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Maſter Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Harriſon. William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. William Fox. Iohn Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. William Woodward.</note>Then came in to ſee her toward euening, Maſter <hi>William Harriſon the Preacher,</hi> praiſing God for her continuance, in that her ioyfull and moſt happie courſe: and perſwading her to an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perſeuerance in the ſame, ſhe thanked him, and deſired him to reioyce in Chriſt with her, and to praiſe God for his mercies to her, and ſaid: <hi>Oh Maſter Harriſon, my ſoule hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about with terrors of death, feare within, &amp; feare without, the ſorrowes of hell were vpon me, knots and knorres were vpon my ſoule,</hi> (which twice or thrice ſhe repeated) <hi>and a roring wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes of woe was within me; but bleſſed, bleſſed, bleſſed, be the Lord my God, who hath not left me comfortleſſe, but like a good ſhepheard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>hath hee brought mee into a place of reſt, euen no the ſweete running waters of life, that flow out of the ſanctuarie of God, and hee hath led me into the greene paſtures, where I am fed, and exceedingly comforted: yea, he hath reſtored my ſoule, and lead me into the plaine and eaſie paths of righteouſnes. The way that now I goe in, is a ſweet and eaſie way, ſtrowed with flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, and as a fine ſandie way;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 147.14.</note> 
               <hi>yea, it is more eaſie and ſoft then the ſand, for I goe and tread vpon wheate, euen vpon the fineſt flower of wheat: Oh bleſſed be the Lord; Oh bleſſed be the Lord, that hath thus comforted mee, and hath brought mee now to a place, more ſweete vnto me then the Garden of</hi> Eden. <hi>Oh the ioy! the ioy, the delightſome ioy that I feele! Oh how wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, how wonderfull, how wonderfull is this ioy! O praiſe the Lord for his mercies, and for this ioy which my ſoule feeleth full well: praiſe his name for euermore.</hi> And theſe praiſes of God, ſhe ſounded foorth,<note place="margin">William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. William Woodward.</note> like <hi>Dauids</hi> harmonie, being indued with <hi>Dauids</hi> ſpirit, to the praiſe of the eternall and mercifull God, continuing al night in ſuch like prayers and praiſes to God, except ſome ſmal time, that ſhée was ſilent and quiet. Maſter <hi>Harriſon</hi> prayed twice with her that euening, as alſo in the morning <hi>(being Whitſunday.)</hi> After he had prayed once with her, going then to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:27766:11"/>his publike charge, ſhe ſent for him to pray once more with her before hee went, which hee did; to the ioy and gladneſſe of heart, both of her, and al that were preſent: and ſo he tooke leaue of her, and departed.</p>
            <p>Another faithfull man or two came preſentlie in that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and diuers others well affected,<note place="margin">M. Edward Aſpinwall. William Fox. William Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. Iohn Bret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergh. William Woodward. Miſtris Maud Brettergh. Miſtris Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtica Fox. Elizabeth Challoner, and diuers moe. Pſal. 30.10.11.12.</note> who were with her at the time of her death, and often prayed with her that forenoone, ſhée ſtill abounding in ſpiritual comforts and conſolations: ſomtimes as one awaking out of ſleepe, ſhée would ſay, <hi>the Lord was her keeper, and deliuerer.</hi> Againe, one ſaying vnto her, the Lord bleſſe you: <hi>Yea</hi> (ſaith ſhée) <hi>and the Lord Ieſus bleſſe vs all.</hi> And ſo ſeeming to ſleepe a little while, and awaking againe ſhe ſaid: <hi>Lord I truſt in thee, haue mercy vpon me, giue me ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to praiſe thee: defend and preſerue me in the houre of tentation, and lay no more vpon me, then thou wilt inable me to beare.</hi> Afterwards being aſked, if ſhe would haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ioyne in praier together again with her: <hi>O yes</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>for Chriſts ſake I deſire it:</hi> ſaying thus to her ſelfe: <hi>Heare O Lord, and haue mercie vpon me: Lord bee thou my helper. Thou haſt looſed my ſacke, and girded me with gladneſſe: therfore will I praiſe thee, O Lord my God: I will giue thankes to thee for euermore.</hi> With that, all that were preſent did ioyne in prayer with her, and in concluſion vſing the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> which ſhe ſaid with them, to <hi>thine is the kingdome;</hi> her ſtrength then being gone, her tongue failed her, and ſo ſhee lay ſilent for a while, euery one iudging her then to bee neere death, her ſtrength and ſpeech failing her: yet after a while, lifting vp her eyes with a ſweete countenance and ſtill voyce, ſaid:<note place="margin">Eſa. 40.2. Pſal. 73.25.26.</note> 
               <hi>My warrefare is accompliſhed, and my iniquities are pardoned. Lord whom haue I in heauen but thee? and I haue none in earth but thee: my fleſh faileth, and my heart alſo, but God is the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for euer. He that preſerueth Iacob, and defendeth his Iſrael, hee is my God, and will guide me vnto death: guide me O Lord my God, and ſuffer me not to faint, but keepe my ſoule in ſafetie.</hi> And with that ſhe preſently fell aſleepe in the Lord, paſſing away in peace, without any motion of bodie at all; and ſo yeelded vp the Ghoſt, a ſweete Sabbaths ſacrifice about foure of the clocke in the afternoone, of <hi>Whitſunday,</hi> being the laſt of <hi>May, 1601.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:27766:12"/>
            <p> This was the death of that vertuous Gentlewoman, happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie dying in the Lord, and reaping the benefit of a holie profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Wherein wee cannot but acknowledge and reuerence the mercie of God, who in our greateſt infirmity makes his grace to ſhine moſt cléerely. A ſure teſtimonie of the truth of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſeruing to incourage vs therein, and to moue vs to a godlie life. It muſt néedes bee a diuine Religion, and a true, comming from God, that thus can fill the heart and mouth of a weake wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, at the time of death, with ſuch admirable comfort. And a wretched conceite, and meere Antichriſtian is that religion, which ſo hateth and perſecuteth this faith, which is thus able to leade the true-hearted profeſſors thereof, with ſuch vnſpeakeable peace vnto their graues.</p>
            <p>Her Funerall was accompliſhed at <hi>Childwall</hi> Church on Wedneſday following, being the third of <hi>Iune.</hi> And now for concluſion, ſeeing this bleſſed Gentlewoman is taken from among vs, and receiued into the holy habitations of the heauenly Ieruſalem, there to remaine in ioy, glorie, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes for euermore; let vs lament for our leſſe, but reioice for her gaine; and let vs pray, that in heart we could as willingly wiſh to be with her, as ſhe is now vnwilling to be with vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The memorie of the iuſt ſhall be bleſſed: but the name of the wicked ſhall rot. Prou. 10.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27766:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
